

Shameel Arafin algebraist@gmail.com shameelarafin.com (215) 982-0854

> LinkedIn shameelarafin Twitter @algebraist

Shameel Arafin

Executive with extensive strategic and operational experience in technology, media, education and finance. Consensus-builder in high-pressure environments, program manager at scale. Domain expertise focused on media streaming and distribution (ondemand and live); app development (iOS, Android, Roku, FireTV, web); digital journalism (platform/CMS, and storytelling), and EdTech. Leader, educator, mentor, engineering gender-parity advocate. 10+ years in software engineering, product management, digital strategy, and large-scale project development. Former investment banker.

Experience

Fortune Media

September 2019 - Present

Vice President, Product

- Report directly to the CTO, responsible for delivery of all Fortune Premium digital products and services: Subscription, Video Portal, Website, Mobile Apps, Conferences, Connect.
- Operational oversight for Product and Engineering teams' efforts in the digital transformation of Fortune from legacy publisher to multi-platform media com-
- Interface between C-suite executives, and all strategic stakeholders: Editorial, Sales, Marketing, Operations, Product and Engineering.

ViewLift

December 2018 - July 2019

Vice President, Engineering

- Report directly to the President, responsible for platform and client technology.
- Build and maintain core platform for digital distribution of live and on-demand content. Build and maintain client apps across all devices (iOS, Android, Roku, FireTV, etc.) Clients include NBCUniversal (streaming media), Monumental Sports Network (sports statistics and betting), NEOU (fitness).
- Manage distributed, global team of two dozen engineers (New York, India).

Meredith Corp. (formerly Time Inc.) August 2015 - February 2018

Senior Director, Platform Engineering, News Group

- Led engineering teams for News, Health and Education verticals, as well as branded content/native advertising efforts. Delivered multimillion-dollar engagements, working closely with editorial, advertising and marketing teams. Clients included Netflix and Siemens (seven-figure engagement).
- Responsible for all technological aspects of time.com, fortune.com, money.com, timeforkids.com, health.com and other brands, at scale - a portfolio that delivered hundreds of millions of monthly unique visitors.
- Successfully launched multiple award-winning projects, including TIME's Person of the Year "The Silence Breakers" and "Finding Home", winner of American Society of Magazine Editors (ASME) award, Picture of the Year (POY) award, and Edward R. Murrow award; Emmy-nominated.
- Drove re-architecture, re-platforming and development of Time For Kids, transforming it into an EdTech learning management system (LMS). Features include multiple lexile levels, translations, audio read-aloud, and online-assessment.
- Recruited and led over a dozen developers, growing a team from 2 to 14 members, whose composition approached gender parity (43% female). Deeply involved in mentoring Product, Design and Engineering departments.

MediaStorm

June 2011 - July 2015

Platform Architect & Lead Developer

- Created architecture and back-end development for MediaStorm Platform, a cinematic, interactive storytelling tool.
- First online video player to implement transaction (pay to view), built on proprietary CMS — featured in TIME magazine. Key users/clients include Wall Street Journal, Sundance Institute, International Center for Transitional Justice.
- Led technology sections for MediaStorm Workshops.
- Recruited developers and interns. Initiated 401(k) plan.



Shameel Arafin algebraist@gmail.com shameelarafin.com (215) 982-0854

 $\begin{array}{c} \textbf{LinkedIn} \\ \textbf{shame} \textbf{elarafin} \\ \textbf{Twitter} \\ \textbf{@algebraist} \end{array}$

CUNY, New Jersey Institute of Technology

Winter 2015 - Present

Data Science & Artificial Intelligence Research/Instructor

- Tech-In-Residence Corps: Working to fulfill Mayor's goal of supporting a pipeline of local talent pursuing tech degrees at CUNY, by developing curriculum and mentoring.
- Consulting with NJIT's Director of Data Science and Bioinformatics. Researching machine learning algorithms for fake news detection.

SignalFive

September 2008 - June 2011

Co-Founder, CTO

- Co-founded SignalFive, an interactive design, development and strategy agency for web and mobile apps. Responsibilities included all aspects of entrepreneurship, from accounting (developed proprietary in-house invoicing system) to business development (led eight interns one summer) to RFPs (pitched FreshDirect).
- Clients included Al Gore's Alliance for Climate Protection . Built a multimedia app driven by citizen- and documentary video journalism.
- As an agency, developed various iPhone apps for clients such as Grand Marnier. Architected and coded prototype of PopStay, a social app for vacation-rentals and home-swapping (before AirBnB became the gorilla in the space).

Massify

September 2007 - September 2008

Developer, Project Manager

- Back-end developer at Icahn-funded startup, a social network/ crowd-sourcing web application for the film and TV industry.
- Reported to CTO, worked with team to build and launch the beta version of Massify.com, which launched in November 2007, followed by a full launch a few months later.

Freelance Developer

December 2002 - June 2008

 $Software\ Engineer$

• Various projects, including full re-design, re-platforming and re-launch of Mercy Health System's websites throughout the greater Philadelphia area (14 websites launched simultaneously).

Credit Suisse First Boston Tech Group

July 1998 - March 2002

 $Senior\ Research\ Associate$

• Equity research in Semiconductor Capital Equipment and Communications Test & Measurement sectors.

Deutsche Bank Securities Tech Group

June 1997 - July 1998

Research Assistant

• Research Assistant to Director of Research/Lead Analyst on PC Hardware & Software. Editor of *The Tech Daily*.

Certifications

Scrum Alliance

February 2018 - February 2020

 $Certified\ Scrum\ Product\ Owner$

Education

Harvard University

September 1995 - June 1997

B.A. Literature (Honors)

California Institute of Technology

September 1993 - June 1995

Electrical Engineering / Literature candidate

Interests

• Publishing, Documentary video, Running, Photography